Guide to the Time Inc. People Editorial Files 1966-1989 MS 3009-RG 10
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. People Editorial Records
1966-1989
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 10
6 Linear feet in 5 record cartons, 1 flat box
The People Editorial Records contain records from offices and staff from the editorial side of the magazine, not the publishing or business side. Editorial staff represented include Cranston Jones, Lee Wohlfert, Marianne Macy, Martha Babcock, Sarah Rozen, Richard Stolley, and Dick Lemon.
Biographical / Historical
People magazine was launched as a newsstand-only publication on March 4, 1974, with Richard B. Stolley as the founding managing editor and Richard Durrell as the founding publisher. People was created under the Magazine Development Group, divesting and becoming its own department by 1978. Because the magazine was so dependent on newssstand sales, Stolley created this guideline for choosing cover subjects: "Young is better than old, pretty is better than ugly, television is better than music, music is better than movies, movies are better than sports, and anything is better than politics." People magazine exceeded sales of one million copies per issue by July 1974.
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Editorial includes the editors, researchers, and art department. The editorial side reported up to the editor-in-chief and the publishing/business side reported up to the corporate business executive which was the president prior to 1960 and the chief executive officer after. Henry Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
Citation:
Bernstein, Lester. "Time Inc. Means Business." The New York Times Magazine, 26 February 1989.
Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Scope and Contents
The People Editorial Records contain records from offices and staff from the editorial side of the magazine, not the publishing or business side. Editorial staff represented include Cranston Jones, Lee Wohlfert, Marianne Macy, Martha Babcock, Sarah Rozen, Richard Stolley, and Dick Lemon.
Records include memoranda, correspondence, book drafts for Best of People, article research, copies of books used in Wohlfert's research, news clippings, photographs, publishing budgets, Home Box Office's (HBO) Best of People television special script, and article drafts.
Arrangement
The materials within the Time Inc. Subject Files record group are organized into three series based on hierarchy of job titles with general office files at the end:
Series I. Senior Editor Cranston Jones Files on Best of People
Series II. Writer Lee Wohlfert Files
Series III. People Magazine 50th Television Anniversary Issue Files
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Materials created within the past 35 years also may be subject to restriction on a case-by-case basis. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time, Inc. in 2015.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other records groups and overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of People and additional records from the editorial offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39). Records from the publishing and business offices are in the Time Inc. People Publishing and Business Records (MS 3009-RG 27).
Books; Corporation records.; Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Journalists -- United States.; Magazines (periodicals).; Organization files.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Jones, Cranston, 1918-1991; Wohlfert, Lee; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History
- Series I. Senior Editor Cranston Jones Files on Best of People, 1977-1984; 1 Linear feet in 1 record carton
  Biographical / Historical
  Cranston Jones was a staff member of Time from 1945 to 1969, serving variously as a correspondent in San Francisco, London and Paris and as bureau chief in Rio de Janeiro. He was editor in chief of Travel and Leisure magazine for several years and then a senior editor with People from its founding in 1974 until he retired in 1988.
  Best of People: The First Decade was a retrospective of notable People covers, subjects, and articles from 1974 to 1983. It was published in softcover by Ballantine Books, an imprint of Random House; a hardcover edition was published by Time-Life Books.
  Citation:
  Flint, Peter B. "Cranston Jones, 73, Architecture Author And Writer at Time." New York Times. June 03, 1991. Accessed November 16, 2018. https://www.nytimes.com/1991/06/03/obituaries/cranston-jones-73-architecture-author-and-writer-at-time.html.
  Scope and Contents
  The Cranston Jones Files on Best of People include materials such as memoranda, correspondence, book drafts, Table of Contents, publishing budgets, Home Box Office's (HBO) Best of People television special script, founding People managing editor Richard Stolley's book introduction, weekly progress reports, and legal correspondence regarding obtaining photographic and distribution rights out of the United States. Notable correspondents are: Stolley; editor Pat Ryan; and publisher Richard Durrell.
  People Polls refers to results of an annual nationwide reader survey on celebrities, politics, fashion, and culture. People Staff Polls refers to an internal survey on what should be included in the book.
  Correspondence includes some with Amanda Urban, the project's literary agent at International Creative Management, Inc. (ICM). Amanda is also sometimes referred to as "Binky".
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Amanda Urban at International Creative Management (ICM), 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 1)
  - Artists, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 2)
  - Ballantine Books, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 3)
  - Budgets, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 4)
  - C. Jones File: Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 5)
  - Contents: Expanded Version for Publisher's Presentation, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Best of People, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 7)
  - Copyright/Title Page, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 8)
  - Covers, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 9)
  - Covers: The Great Covers: Mega 25, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 10)
  - Home Box Office (HBO), 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 11)
  - Introduction by Richard B. Stolley, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 12-13)
  - Legal, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 15)
  - Mega Celebs: The Decade's 25, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 16)
  - People Polls, 1980-1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 17)
  - People Staff Polls, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 18)
  - Super Star Tracks, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 19)
  - Table of Contents Draft, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 20)
  - Time-Life Books, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 21)
  - Weekly Progress Report, 1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 22)
  - Winners and Losers, 1977-1983 (Offsite-box 2847, Folder 23)
- Series II. Writer Lee Wohlfert Files, 1979-1983; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons, 1 flat box
  Lee Wohlfert started as a People magazine writer in 1974 and was made Assistant Editor in February 1983. She continued to write articles following her promotion and the materials in this series are concerned only with her writing. She is credited as Lee Wohlfert-Wihlborg in the People masthead. Wolhfert also freelanced for publications such as Town & Country, Harper's Bazaaar, and LA Style.
  She left People in 1986, but continued to freelance for the magazine until 1990. While she published under the last names "Wohlfert" and "Wohlfert-Wihlborg" after 1983, she currently goes by Wohlfert.
  Wohlfert, Lee. User profile, LinkedIn. Accessed November 16, 2018. https://www.linkedin.com/in/lee-wohlfert-07982619/.
  Materials are from Lee Wohlfert's time as a People writer, including article drafts and research, news clippings, memorandum, photographs of Arthur Hailey for a 1973 profile, and materials for Miss America Pageant officials. Also includes copies of books by Stephen Gaskin, Tom Wolfe, and Jacqueline and Lee Bouvier; these were used for article research. The articles-related materials are focused on culture and fashion, including published interviews with Sean Young, Diane Von Furstenberg, and Lee Radziwell. Miss America Pageant materials cover the national level and Mississippi. Some notebooks are included in the general articles research with interview questions and thoughts inside; one untitled, undated notebook was found unassociated with any materials and is foldered by itself.
  Includes a copy of Wohlfert's 1978 interview with Anne Beats about Saturday Night Live (SNL) published in Your Place magazine, a McCall's publication aimed at young people of both sexes that was published for only five issues. It is unconnected to Time Inc., and the interview was done as a freelance assignment. Wohlfert continued to collect information on the SNL cast through 1979, including internal memos with People editor Jim Seymore about getting an interview with some of the notoriously press-shy cast.
  - Articles, 1971-1983 (Offsite-box 2844, Folder 1-8)
  - Articles: Casablancas, 1983 (Offsite-box 2844, Folder 9-10)
  - Articles: Lyngstad, Anna-Frid, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 2844, Folder 11)
  - Articles: Miss America Pageant: General, 1983 (Offsite-box 2844, Folder 12)
  - Articles: Miss America Pageant: Mississippi, 1983 (Offsite-box 2844, Folder 13-14)
  - Articles: Miss America Pageant: Official's Materials, 1983 (Offsite-box 2844, Folder 15-16)
  - Articles: Radziwill, Lee, 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 1-2)
  - Articles: Saturday Night Live, 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 3)
  - Articles: Von Furstenberg, Diane, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 4)
  - Bovier, Jacqueline and Lee: One Special Summer, 1974 (Offsite-box 2846, Folder 1)
  - Gaskin, Stephen: Hey, Beatnik! and Monday Night Class, 1974 (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 5)
  - Notebook (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Arthur Hailey, 1973 (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 7)
  - Wolfe, Tom: In Our Time, 1980 (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 8)
  - Your Place Magazine, 1978 October (Offsite-box 2845, Folder 9)
- Series III. People Magazine Television Anniversary Issue Files, 1966-1989; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
  The People Magazine Television Anniversary Issue was published in May 1989 to celebrate the 50th anniversary of the first television broadcast in 1939. Materials were gathered by staff research-reporters starting in 1989, with the first draft of the magazine presented in January 1989. Starting with 7000 photographs and innumerable topics to include, the team edited the material to 750 photos on 129 pages and the cover, along with accompanying articles. Senior editor Richard Sanders and Dick Lemon led the team, with Sarah Rozen doing much of the photographic research. Eight writers composed the text, with three reporter-researchers conducting fact checks.
  Valk, Elizabeth P. "Publisher's Letter." PEOPLE.com. May 4, 1989. Accessed November 19, 2018. https://people.com/archive/publishers-letter/.
  The People Television Anniversary Issue Files include memoranda from staff such as Marianne Macy, Martha Babcock, and Sarah Rozen to Dick Lemon and the People Reporting Staff. Topics include personalities to include in the special and photograph usage. Background research, table of contents drafts, and interview transcripts are included. Interviews were conducted with choice people from the history of television for a section called "Voices". Notable interviewees include Mike Wallace, Bob Pittman, and Ruth Warrick.
  Publishing drafts of articles are included. Most are concerned with a specific person, notably Carol Burnett, Mary Tyler Moore, and Johnny Carson. There were articles written on decades from the 1960s to the 1980s, and on genres such as advertising, westerns, game shows and soap operas.
  The files seem to have been gathered from the special issue staff during the course of publishing by Senior Editors Dick Lemon or Richard Sanders, or Executive Editor Jim Seymour.
  Materials are in original alphabetical order.
  - Acts, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 1)
  - Ads, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 2)
  - Alda, Alan, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 3)
  - Archie, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 4)
  - Arness, James, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 5)
  - Assignments, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 6)
  - Beaver, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 7)
  - Belushi, John, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 8)
  - Berle, Milton, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 9)
  - Broadcast Industry Future, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 10)
  - Brooks, Mel, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 11)
  - Burnett, Carol, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 12)
  - Caesar, Sid, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 13)
  - Carney, Art, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 14)
  - Carson, Johnny, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 15)
  - Clark, Dick, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 16)
  - Cosby, Bill, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 17)
  - Cronkite, Walter, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 18)
  - Cult Shows, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 19)
  - Fawcett, Farrah, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 20)
  - Game Shows, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 21)
  - Garner, James, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 22)
  - Gleason, Jackie, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 23)
  - Hagman, Larry, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 24)
  - History of Sex on TV, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 25)
  - Interviews, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 26)
  - Introduction, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 27)
  - Janssen, David, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 28)
  - Kermit, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 29)
  - Kid's Shows, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 30)
  - Kovacs, Ernie, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 31)
  - Johnson, Don, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 32)
  - Letterman, David, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 33)
  - Locals, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 34)
  - Lucy, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 35)
  - Marshall, Garry, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 36)
  - McLuhan, Marshal, 1966-1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 37)
  - Memorable Moments on TV, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 38)
  - Miller, Nolan, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 39)
  - Moore, Mary Tyler, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 40)
  - News, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 41)
  - Parr, Jack, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 42)
  - Photo List for Sex on TV, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 43)
  - Pittman, Bob, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 44)
  - Question for Sex in TV, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 45)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1989 (Offsite-box 2848, Folder 46)
  - Silverman, Fred, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 1)
  - Soaps, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 2)
  - Sports, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 3)
  - Sullivan, Ed, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 4)
  - Walters, Barbara, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 5)
  - Wolfer, David, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 6)
  - The '40s, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 7)
  - '40s Timeline, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 8)
  - The '50s, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 9-10)
  - '50s Timeline, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 11)
  - '50s Westerns, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 12)
  - The '60s, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 13-14)
  - '60s Timeline, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 15)
  - The '70s, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 16)
  - '70s Timeline, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 17)
  - The '80s, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 18)
  - '80s Timeline, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 19)
  - "Voices" Interviews, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 20-22)
  - "Voices" Section, 1989 (Offsite-box 2849, Folder 23-24)